Three common metrics for species-level biodiversity, encompassing attention to species richness or species evenness

Taxonomic Diversity Metrics
• Species Richness: simply the number of different species represented in an ecological community, landscape, or region
• Simpson's Index: measures the probability that two individuals randomly selected from a sample will belong to the same species. Can include Simpson's Index of Diversity (1-D) as well as Simpson's Reciprocal Index (1/D) (Considers both evenness and abundance)
⁃ Dominance Index: gives more weight to common or dominant species
• Shannon-Wiener Index: Similar to Simpson's index, however is an information statistic index, since it assumes all species are represented in a sample and that they are randomly sampled.
⁃ Quantifies the uncertainty in predicting the species identity of an individual that is taken at random from the dataset 
• New Metric: Mean Species Abundance (MSA): Indicator describing biodiversity changes with reference to the original state of the ecosystem. It is defined as the average abundances of naturally of originally occurring species relative to their abundance in the original, pristine, or mature state as the basis. It is an indicator of biodiversity intactness, and can describe homogenization. 

Scales of Diversity:
• Alpha Diversity: diversity within a particular area, community, or ecosystem. Is measured by counting the number of taxa within the ecosystem (usually species)
• Beta Diversity: species diversity between ecosystems, comparing the number of taxa that are unique to each of the ecosystems
• Gamma Diversity: measurement of the overall diversity for different ecosystems within a region

Traditional Diversity Measures:
• Species Density
• Species Richness
• Diversity Indices
Phylogenetic Diversity Measures:
• Phylogenetic diversity (PD) index
• Topology based measures
⁃ taxonomic distinctiveness
⁃ taxonomic diversity
⁃ taxonomic distinctness

